Guide to the Ladyfest 2000 Collection, 2000-2001 MSS.360
Fales Library and Special Collections
Ladyfest 2000 Collection
2000-2001
Fales Library and Special Collections
Stinson, Beth
Wynkoop, Kanako
Herschelman, Tina
MSS.360
1 Linear Feet in 3 binders, 1 box
The Ladyfest 2000 collection includes photographs, negatives, paste-ups, and ephemera associated with Ladyfest 2000, a non-profit, feminist, music and arts festival that took place in Olympia, Washington in 2000.
Provenance
This collection was donated to the Fales Library & Special Collections by Elizabeth Stinson in 2012 and 2013. Most of the collection consists of materials mailed by festival attendees to festival organizer Tina Herschelman after the festival was over. These materials were stored by festival organizer Kanako Wynkoop at her clothing store Dumpster Values in Olympia until they were brought to New York by festival organizer Elizabeth Stinson and donated to NYU's Fales Library & Special Collections. Other materials were donated by Stinson from her own organizational files in 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Arrangement
This collection arrived with no discernible order and the archivist divided it into four series:
Series I: Photographic Material
Series II: Beth Stinson Material
Series III: Media
Series IV: Data Storage
Series I: Photographic Material
The archivist arranged this series alphabetically by last name of the person who donated the photographic material, if known, and the first name if not known. Some photographs' source is unidentified and they are marked as such.
Series II: Beth Stinson Material
The archivist arranged this series alphabetically by genre of material.
Series III: Media
The archivist arranged this series into subseries by genre, and then alphabetically by the title originally printed on the media itself.
Series IV: Data Storage
This series consists of two unidentified zip disks.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials collected and produced in conjunction with Ladyfest 2000 in Olympia, Washington. The photographic materials were solicited from participants by Ladyfest organizer Tina Herschelman. Organizer Kanako Wynkoop gathered the material together, and organizer Beth Stinson added her own contributions from her time as an organizer and donated the collection to Fales.The collection is divided into four series.
Series I: Photographic Materials
This series consists of photographs sent to Ladyfest organizers. Some of the photos are of artwork and goods that artists hoped to display or sell at Ladyfest, and the vast majority of the photos are candid shots taken at the events of Ladyfest 2000. Photographs, negatives, contact sheets, and slides document musical and artistic performances, as well as more casual moments of the festival. The archivist labeled the files with the name of the person who sent the materials, if known.
Series II: Beth Stinson Materials
These materials include ephemera, paste-ups, and mock-ups of festival booklets and ephemera generated in conjunction with Ladyfest that Beth Stinson, one of the organizers of the festival, collected.
Series III: Media
This series consists of digital video and audio tapes documenting the planning process and the performances at Ladyfest 2000.
Series IV: Data Storage
This series consists of two unlabeled zip disks.
Historical Note
Ladyfest 2000 was a non-profit, community-based event organized by and for women to showcase, celebrate and encourage the artistic, organizational and political work and talents of women. Taking place in Olympia, Washington from August 1 to August 6, 2000, Ladyfest featured performances by bands, spoken word artists, and writers, as well as workshops, panels, art shows and dance parties.
The inspiration for Ladyfest arose in part when some former members of the feminist Riot Grrrl movement were interviewed for Seattle's Experience Music Riot Grrrl Retrospective oral history project in 1999. Looking back at their participation in Riot Grrrl, and in light of the sexual assaults that had happened at the 1999 Woodstock festival, they were motivated to create a festival that created a safe and inspirational space for women's performance and activism.
Ladyfest was organized and run entirely by volunteers. Initial meetings began in fall 1999. By the third meeting in January 2000, around 35 prospective organizers attended, and committees on Budget, Volunteer coordinating, Booking, Merchandise, Workshops, Visual Art, Performance, Documentation and Web Site Creation had been formed. The festival drew over 2,000 attendees, and included performances by Bratmobile, Sleater-Kinney, The Gossip and Cat Power. Workshops were given on auto mechanics, letterpress, gardening, and dismantling racism. Other events included a fashion show, a drag show, art openings, and a sewing circle. Ladyfest was a woman-run event, but all were welcome to attend. Events listed as "ladies only" were open to all women, including women who identified as men, and ladies who were born male. Since 2000, over 100 Ladyfest festivals inspired by Ladyfest 2000 have taken place worldwide, including in Australia, France, Indonesia, South Africa, and Switzerland. The meeting minutes have been archived at the Ladyfest website (http://www.ladyfest.org/planning/index.html#1230).
Related Materials
Teresa Carmody Ladyfest 2000 Collection (MSS.389)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and are unavailable to researchers.
Workshops (seminars); Alternative spaces (Arts facilities).; LGBTQ+ activism; Feminist music; Feminism; Community arts projects -- United States.; Women artists -- Exhibitions.; Riot grrrl movement.; Performance art.; Olympia (Wash.); Artists -- Exhibitions
- Series I: Photographic Material
  Scope and Content
  This series is made up of photographs sent to Ladyfest organizer Tina Heschelman from organizers and participants in the event, after it was over. The materials include photographs, negatives, contact sheets, slides and the accompanying envelopes and correspondence found with the photographic material.
  - Matt Alcock, [2000] (Binder A)
  - Matt Alcock, 2000 (Binder A)
  - Amanda, [2000] (Binder A)
  - Diana Arens and Andrew Austin, 2000 (Binder A)
  - Amber Bales, 2000 (Binder A)
  - Kate Berkemeyer, 2000-2001 (Binder A)
  - Christopher Braiotta and Emily Arkin, 2000-2001 (Binder A)
  - J.E. Brown, 2000 (Binder A)
  - Rocío Carlos, 2000 (Binder A)
  - Dave Chenoweth, 2000 (Binder A)
  - Amina Cruz, 2000 (Binder B)
  - Krista Gregory, 2000 (Binder B)
  - Faith Hagenhofer, 2000 (Binder B)
  - Jamie Hamilton, 2000 (Binder B)
  - Kathryn Lewis, [2000] (Binder B)
  - Stephanie Melikian and Lisa Lowenfels, 2000 (Binder C)
  - Melissa D. Neal, 2000 (Binder C)
  - Tod A. Seelie, 2000 (Binder C)
  - Unidentified, 2000 (Binder C)
  - Unidentified, [2000] (Binder C)
  - Unidentified, [2000] (Binder C)
  - Lori Vaughn, 2000 (Binder C)
- Series II: Beth Stinson Material
  This series is made up of material collected and/or created by Beth Stinson in her role as an organizer of Ladyfest 2000. The materials include paste-ups, mock-ups, and ephemera.
  - Ladyfest Brochure Printout, [2000] (Binder C)
  - Ladyfest Ephemera, 2000 (Binder C)
  - Ladyfest Paste-Ups, 2000 (Binder C)
- Series III: Media
  This series consists of cassette and mini dv tapes documenting events held at Ladyfest 2000 most of which were sent to Ladyfest organizer Tina Herschelman after the festival was over.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - Penny Arcade Side A, [2000] (Box 1, Item ID: 360.0001)
    Currently unavailable.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    Original Format: Audiocassette
  - Penny Arcade Interview, [2000] (Box 1, Item ID: 360.0002)
  - Spoken Word @ Midnight Sun, [2000] (Box 1, Item ID: 360.0003)
  - Spoken Word @ Midnight Sun, [2000] (Box 1, Item ID: 360.0004)
    Original Format: audiocassette
  - Drag Show, [2000] (Box 1, Item ID: 360.0005)
    Original Format: Mini-DV
    Running Time: 11:04:19 Start 00:09:06 End 11:13:25
  - Spoken Word + Drag, [2000] (Box 1, Item ID: 360.0006)
    See also: Box 1, Folder 1
    Subtitle: Ladyfest 2000 Spoken Word, Dude-Looks-Like-A-Lady-Fest
    Shot List: Art Cheerleaders Stacey Ann Chin Nicole Blackman Spider Inga Muscio Teresa Carmody Penny Arcade Art Cheerleaders Dude-Looks-Like-A-Lady-Fest
  - Letter and Shot List for Video ID 360.0006, [2000] (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Data Storage
  This series consists of 2 unidentified zip disks.
  Born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - Unidentified, Undated (Box 1, Disk 360.3.0001)
  - Unidentified, Undated (Box 1, Disk 360.3.0002)